{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this city built the fortress of Ortygia. During a festival to Artemis, this city was captured by Marcus Claudius Marcellus after a protracted siege. A general from this city named Hicetas took control of this city, only to be removed from power by Timoleon. Two tyrants name Dionysius ruled this city, which was home to a scientist who supposedly built a giant claw and heat ray to defend it. For 10 points, name this home of Archimedes, a city on Sicily.",
      "answer": "Syracuse <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This scandal was initially prosecuted by General John Brooks Henderson, who was later dismissed. A trial stemming from this scandal forced the St. Louis courtroom to be expanded to fit all the reporters. It involved General Orville Babcock, who was eventually exposed by Secretary of the Treasury Benjamin Bristow. For 10 points, name this scandal for the Grant administration in which federal tax revenues on liquor were illegally diverted.",
      "answer": "Whiskey Ring <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king drove back attempts by another nation's Henry III to invade France, including at the Battle of Taillebourg. This king's brother Robert of Artois was killed during a battle at Al- Mansurah, which was fought after the capture of Damietta. This king commissioned the construction of the Sainte-Chapelle, in which he placed the Crown of Thorns. This son of Blanche of Castile participated in the Seventh and Eighth Crusades. For 10 points, name this canonized French king.",
      "answer": "Louis IX <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's leadership was the subject of the book A State of Blood. This leader's health minister, Henry Kyemba, defected to the U.K. He was served by Bob Astles, the \"White Rat.\" This leader took power in a coup begun while President Milton Obote (pr. oh-BOE-tay) was out of the country. This man expelled 60,000 South Asians from his country in 1972 and lost power in a failed war with Tanzania. For 10 points, name this dictator of Uganda who was deposed in 1979.",
      "answer": "Idi Amin Dada <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "It's not Kentucky, but a movie about a team from this state featured Jon Voight as Coach Adolph Rupp. A team from this state was the focus of the film Glory Road, starring Josh Lucas as Coach Don Haskins. A university from this state defeated Kentucky in 1966 to mark the first time that a college basketball team with five black starters won a title. For 10 points, name this Southern state where the school that is now the UTEP Miners plays games in El Paso.",
      "answer": "Texas <MC> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    },
    {
      "question": "Arthur Krock helped lead the lobbying efforts for this book to win the Pulitzer Prize. It was written while the author was recovering from back surgery, and columnist Drew Pearson claimed that Ted Sorenson actually wrote this book. This book looks at Edmund Ross, who broke party lines to vote for acquittal during Andrew Johnson's impeachment. For 10 points, name this collection of short biographies of U.S. Senators written by John F. Kennedy.",
      "answer": "Profiles in Courage <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event resulted in a brief arrest of Guillaume Apollinaire. This action was first brought to attention by Louis Beroud. It was resolved when an ad by Alfredo Geri found its way to investigators. This action was carried out by hiding in a closet overnight, then hiding the central painting inside under artist's smocks. It was perpetrated by Vincenzo Peruggia. For 10 points, name this 1911 incident in which a painting by Leonardo da Vinci was stolen from the Louvre.",
      "answer": "theft of the Mona Lisa <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early Christmas Day air raid during this war targeted an enemy fleet docked at Cuxhaven. During this war, pamphlets in the colors of the Italian flag were dropped over Vienna by Gabriele (pr. gah-bree-AY-lay) d'Annunzio. This war's Battle of Arras (pr. uh-RAH) was known as \"Bloody April\" to the British. The first major wartime use of zeppelins and Fokker aircraft occurred during this conflict. For 10 points, name this war in which the Red Baron shot down over eighty enemy planes.",
      "answer": "World War I <KG> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man left his position as Chief Qadi of the Maldives after locals ignored his complaints about women going topless. This man helped return the wife of Ozbeg Khan to her home city of Constantinople. After leaving the service of Muhammad bin Tughluq, this man visited the Yuan Dynasty capital of Khanbaliq before returning to his hometown of Tangier. For 10 points, name this 14th century Moroccan who documented his travels across much of Asia and Africa.",
      "answer": "Ibn Battuta <TR> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Francis Dana declined to join the main group in this event. Pierre Bellamy suggested during this event that people make purchases at inflated prices. After this event, a man privately met with Elbridge Gerry at a dinner, seeking to separate him from his confederates. During it, Charles Pinckney reportedly said \"no, no, not a sixpence!\" to Talleyrand's agents. For 10 points, name this 1797 event in which three anonymous French diplomats seemingly requested a bribe from Americans.",
      "answer": "The XYZ Affair <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was the executive president of the Russell Tribunal, which investigated American war crimes in Vietnam. This man called Che Guevara “the most complete human being of our age,” and wrote a preface to Frantz Fanon’s anti-colonial The Wretched Of the Earth. This former POW of the Germans described his philosophy as \"a humanism” in one lecture after he developed the concept of “bad faith.” For 10 points, name this existentialist philosopher of Being and Nothingness.",
      "answer": "Jean-Paul Sartre <CW> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, an outlaw known as \"Five-Fingered Jack\" tortured Cowie and Fowler to death. This conflict was ended by the arrival of John Sloat's squadron. During this conflict, Mariano Vallejo (pr. vye-YAY-ho) was arrested by a party led by \"Stuttering Zeke\" Merritt and William Ide. This rebellion occurred in Sonoma and was encouraged by the \"Pathfinder,\" John C. Fremont. For 10 points, name this 1846 revolt in California that adopted a grizzly as its symbol.",
      "answer": "Bear Flag Revolt <JB> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Some members of the losing side in this battle fled to Evagoras. Philocles was killed at this battle, from which the ship Paralus brought news of one side’s defeat. The losers in this battle had their base at Sestos, following Alcibiades' advice, and were killed in a surprise attack while foraging. Conon survived this battle, in which the Delian League lost 170 triremes. For 10 points, name this decisive battle which was won by Lysander, ending the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Aegospotami"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another important Spartan commander, Brasidas, was a member of what Spartan slave class, members of which could be killed with impunity by the Krypteia?",
        "answer": "Helot <JZ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Cubs outfielder Rick Monday prevented people from doing this action at a 1976 game. Gregory Lee Johnson was arrested for performing this action at the 1984 Republican National Convention. It was protected as free speech in the case Texas v. Johnson, which prompted William Rehnquist to decry attacks on \"the visible symbol embodying our Nation.\" For 10 points, name this action which involves symbolic, incendiary destruction of an iconic object.",
        "answer": "burning the American flag"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What liberal Supreme Court judge also wrote a dissenting opinion in Texas vs. Johnson and served from 1975 to 2010, until he was replaced by Elena Kagan?",
        "answer": "John Paul Stevens <MC> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Karl Bischoff is best known for supervising an expansion in construction at this location. Memories of this place inspired logotherapy, a type of existential psychotherapy developed by Viktor Frankl. The Monowitz facility expanded this place, where new people were brought to the \"ramp.\" This was the largest place with an entry gate displaying the message \"Arbeit macht frei\". For 10 points, name this site in Poland, which executed more people than any other Nazi death camp.",
        "answer": "Auschwitz-Birkenau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Auschwitz killed most of what large northern Greek city's Sephardic Jewish community, which thrived under Ottoman rule?",
        "answer": "Salonica <MJ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many of this act’s powers were removed in the Financial Services Modernization Act, or the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act. This act created an organization that pooled money from various banks to insure deposits, the FDIC. Paul Krugman claims its partial repeal in 1999 made the markets vulnerable to the 2008 financial crisis. A former Treasury Secretary was one of its two namesake Senate cosponsors. For 10 points, name this emergency 1933 act that cushioned the impact from bank failures.",
        "answer": "Glass-Steagall Act"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Carter Glass also cosponsored a 1913 bill with Robert Owen which founded what banking organization during the Wilson administration?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve <VP> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This conflict began after the capture of the ship Tacuari. Rutherford B. Hayes helped to arbitrate the treaty ending this conflict. The losing leader in this conflict was killed at the Battle of Cerro Cora, but his Irish mistress Eliza Lynch lived. The naval battle of Riachuelo was fought during it. At this war's star, one side was led by Bartolome Mitre against Francisco Solano Lopez. For 10 points, name this war in which Paraguay was defeated by a namesake coalition.",
        "answer": "War of the Triple Alliance"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Triple Alliance was also caused by Brazil’s invasion of what country, which became independent from Brazil in the Cisplatine War, to support its Colorado Party?",
        "answer": "Uruguay <JZ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Covey was used by Willard Gibbs as a translator in this case. Thomas Gedney sought salvage rights in this event, and Celestino and Ramon Ferrer were killed by forces led by Cinque in it. In the case caused by this event, Henry Gilpin’s argument was defeated by Roger Baldwin, and the majority opinion was written by Joseph Story. For 10 points, name this incident where the Taney (pr. TAW-nee) Court ruled in favor of a group of slaves who mutinied on a namesake Cuban ship.",
        "answer": "Amistad affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The men who mutinied on the Amistad were from what modern day country whose capital was founded by former British slaves?",
        "answer": "Sierra Leone <JZ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1934, Lithuanian-born noble Boris Skossyeff tried to declare himself King Boris I of this nation. A series of medieval agreements called paréages, starting in 1278, still determine the status of this country. A miter hat in the upper left of its coat of arms represents the Bishop of Urgell, a de jure leader of this country in tandem with a secular President of the country to its northeast. For 10 points, name this principality in the Pyrenees between Spain and France.",
        "answer": "Principality of Andorra"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Andorra's Granvalira and Vallnord areas have brought in foreign currency through what type of tourist attraction, exemplified elsewhere by Steamboat Springs and Telluride?",
        "answer": "ski resorts <MJ> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man lost his position as secretary of state after the assassination of Concino Concini. This man married off his niece to the nephew of the “great” Condé the year before he was targeted by the conspiracy of Cinq-Mars. This man was targeted by the Day of the Dupes, which was orchestrated by Marie de Médici. He besieged La Rochelle, the last Huguenot stronghold. For 10 points, name this cardinal who served as chief minister to King Louis XIII.",
        "answer": "Armand-Jean du Plessis, cardinal et duc de Richelieu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the death of Richelieu, what other cardinal served as regent early in the reign of Louis XIV?",
        "answer": "Jules, Cardinal Mazarin <SH> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "His debut single was inspired by the story of a twelve-year-old putting her child in a trash compactor. He dedicated one song to a 15-year-old whose murder helped spark the L.A. riots, Latasha Harlins. This artist of “Brenda’s Got A Baby” and “Keep Ya Head Up” boasted that he’s “out on bail/fresh outta jail” in another song, whose chorus boasts that his state “know’s how to party”. For 10 points, what rapper of “California Love” was murdered while riding in a car with Suge Knight and feuded with the Notorious B.I.G.?",
        "answer": "Tupac Shakur"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tupac’s posthumous song “Changes” samples what song by Bruce Hornsby and the Range about the civil rights movement?",
        "answer": "“The Way It Is” <CW> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man is the subject of the documentary An Unreasonable Man. This writer analyzed the \"Powerglide\" transmission in a groundbreaking book featuring the chapter \"Disaster deferred.\" This man's student task force, his namesake \"raiders,\" wrote reports attacking government corruption. He critiqued the Corvair in his 1965 book Unsafe at Any Speed. For 10 points, name this two time Green Party presidential nominee, a consumer protection advocate.",
        "answer": "Ralph Nader"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nader attacked the Corvair, a car made by what automobile division of General Motors?",
        "answer": "Chevrolet <MC> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Lobbying on this man's behalf prevented Lewis Strauss from getting a Cabinet position. This man had his security clearance and connections to the AEC suspended in 1953 on suspicion of his Communist sympathies. After seeing the Trinity test in New Mexico, he remarked \"Now I am become Death, the destroyer of worlds.\" For 10 points, name this scientist who headed the secret weapons laboratory as part of the Manhattan Project that made the atomic bomb.",
        "answer": "Julius Robert Oppenheimer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Oppenheimer was disliked by what fellow physicist, the Hungarian born “father of the hydrogen bomb”?",
        "answer": "Edward Teller <MC> {II}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The final verse of one of this author’s poems exhorts “Shake your chains to earth like dew...Ye are many, they are few.” This author's poetic response to the Peterloo Massacre is titled The Masque of Anarchy. The speaker of another poem by this author meets “a traveller from an antique land,” who tells of a pedestal in the desert that says “Look on my works, ye Mighty, and despair!” For 10 points, name this British Romantic poet who used an alternate name of Rameses II to title his \"Ozymandias.\".",
        "answer": "Percy Bysshe Shelley"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shelley drowned in a boat named the Don Juan in homage to what other poet, who wrote Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage and died fighting in the Greek War of Independence?",
        "answer": "George Gordon Byron <SH> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "YORKTOWN",
      "prompt": "Name the yorktown...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the last major land battle of what conflict?",
          "answer": "American Revolutionary War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set up what 1783 peace treaty between Britain and the U.S.?",
          "answer": "Treaty of Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Featured what French Marquis and future Estates General member?",
          "answer": "Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resulted in the capture of what British lord and Lieutenant General?",
          "answer": "Charles Cornwallis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led to what Prime Minister shouting \"It's all over!\"",
          "answer": "Lord North"
        },
        {
          "question": "Featured the French Expeditionary Force led by what nobleman?",
          "answer": "Comte de Rochambeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was preceded by what defeat of Admiral Graves' navy?",
          "answer": "Battle of the Chesapeake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended with British drummers playing what appropriate tune?",
          "answer": "\"The World Turn'd Upside Down\" <MC> {II}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SAMURAI",
      "prompt": "Which…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Type of curved sword was commonly used by samurai?",
          "answer": "katana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man starred in the title role in the film, The Last Samurai?",
          "answer": "Tom Cruise"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern term describes samurai values?",
          "answer": "bushido"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of Buddhism famous for its koans was followed by many samurai?",
          "answer": "Zen Buddhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country’s sailors introduced the arquebus, a gun used during the Sengoku period?",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man directed the film Seven Samurai?",
          "answer": "Akira Kurosawa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary swordsman wrote The Book of Five Rings?",
          "answer": "Miyamoto Musashi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Social class did former samurai join after the Meiji Restoration?",
          "answer": "shizoku <TR> {II}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HISTORY AS SUNG BY BILLY JOEL",
      "prompt": "Name the history as sung by billy joel...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "sang of what largest United States city's \"State of Mind\"?",
          "answer": "New York City"
        },
        {
          "question": "portrayed vets of what war in \"Goodnight Saigon\"?",
          "answer": "Vietnam War"
        },
        {
          "question": "sang \"Say Goodbye to\" what California neighborhood where Paramount's studios are?",
          "answer": "Hollywoodland"
        },
        {
          "question": "began \"We Didn't Start the Fire\" with what president's name?",
          "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "ended \"We Didn't Start the Fire\"'s last verse with what five-word exclamation?",
          "answer": "\"I can't take it anymore!\""
        },
        {
          "question": "recorded what song about fired \"iron, coke, chromium, steel\" workers in Pennsylvania?",
          "answer": "\"Allentown\""
        },
        {
          "question": "titled a song for what Soviet city where a \"child of sacrifice\" named Viktor was born in 1944?",
          "answer": "Leningrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "played what kind of New England worker who \"can't sell no stripers\" in \"The Downeaster Alexa\"?",
          "answer": "commercial fisherman <MJ> {II}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the last stages of this battle, Jean Auguste Margueritte led a failed cavalry charge on Floing. This battle was preceded by the Battle of Beaumont. Fighting in this battle began at Bazeilles (pr. buh-ZAY). During this battle, one side faced brief confusion over whether Auguste-Alexandre Ducrot or General Wimpffen was supposed to take charge of the Army of (20 pts)",
        "Chalons. In this battle, General MacMahon's forces were defeated by those of (10 pts)",
        "Helmuth von Moltke, leading to the capture of Napoleon III. For 10 points, name this decisive battle in the Franco-Prussian War."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Sedan <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These objects were built by the Ruckers family of Antwerp. During the French Revolution, these objects were burned for firewood at the Paris Conservatoire. The muselaar was a small variety of this instrument. The firm of Pleyel and Co. custom-built one of these for Wanda (20 pts)",
        "Landowska, who revived it in the early 20th century. A treatise on this instrument was written by (10 pts)",
        "Francois Couperin. It has plectrums traditionally made out of quills, and its lack of dynamic contrast eventually led to its obsolescence in favor of the piano. For 10 points, name this Baroque keyboard instrument with plucked strings."
      ],
      "answer": "harpsichord <CW> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The developer of the indigo industry, Eliza Lucas, married a member of this family. Along with Pierce Butler, a politician from this family devised the Fugitive Slave Clause during the Constitutional Convention. A prominent member of this family was the (20 pts)",
        "Federalist candidate in the Presidential Elections of 1804 and 1808. Another politician with this surname negotiated free navigation of the (10 pts)",
        "Mississippi River in an agreement also called the Treaty of San Lorenzo. For 10 points, name this South Carolinian family, whose members included the namesake of a treaty that was signed with Spain."
      ],
      "answer": "Pinckney <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Pamphlets inciting these wars accused one side of early uses of waterboarding on alleged perpetrators of the Amboyna massacre. News of the secret Treaty of Dover re-started these conflicts, whose first and second examples ended with treaties negotiated by (20 pts)",
        "Johan de Witt. They weren't in Ireland, but the first one was the main foreign war launched by (10 pts)",
        "Oliver Cromwell, in response to piracy of merchant ships by a Calvinist republic. For 10 points, name these 17th-century wars between countries which later unified under Queen Mary and William III of Orange."
      ],
      "answer": "Anglo-Dutch wars <MJ> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This religion celebrates a festival named for the garden where its founder announced he was a prophet. That festival of this religion is the Ridván. The founder of this religion gave his first wife the title “The Most Exalted Leaf” and was succeeded by (20 pts)",
        "his son, Abbas Effendi. After being banished to Acre, that founder also wrote this religion’s (10 pts)",
        "Book of Certitude and founded its first Houses of Justice. The forerunner of this religion, who adopted a name meaning “gateway,” was the Bab. For 10 points, name this religion founded by Baha’ullah."
      ],
      "answer": "Baha’i <SH> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Manifesto of the 121 was written in response to this war. Gillo Pontecorvo is best known for directing a film set during this war. One side in this war made use of farmers called felleghas in the Battle of Philippeville. This war resulted in the emigration of many (20 pts)",
        "Pieds-noirs. After torture reports surfaced, Jacques Massu was relieved from leading one side in this war. The (10 pts)",
        "Evian Accords ended this war, which was led on one side by the nationalistic party FLN. For 10 points, name this war in which an African nation gained independence from France."
      ],
      "answer": "Algerian War of Independence <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Grover Whalen was the president of this event, which was held on top of a former ash dump. One building in this event included a diorama entitled “Democracity,” and Maurice Ascalon designed a sculpture here for the (20 pts)",
        "Jewish Palestine Pavilion. Johns Mansville promoted asbestos as the “magic mineral” here. One exhibition in this event was designed by (10 pts)",
        "Norman Bel Geddes and imagined a system of automated highways. General Motors sponsored the Futurama exhibit here, and its symbol was the Trylon and Perisphere. For 10 points, what Depression-era exposition was held, like the 1964-1965 version, in Queens’ Flushing Meadows?"
      ],
      "answer": "1939-1940 World’s Fair <CW> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 2000's, several political parties in this non-U.S. country joined together to form the National Rainbow Coalition. The first president of this country followed a doctrine of \"pulling together\" called (20 pts)",
        "Harambee. To challenge this country's ruling political party, FORD was created by Luo chieftain Oginga Odinga. This country's second leader was (10 pts)",
        "Daniel arap Moi, who discriminated against this country's Kikuyu people. The Mau Mau uprising took place in this country. For 10 points, name this African country, whose first president was Jomo Kenyatta."
      ],
      "answer": "Kenya <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ademar de Chabannes recorded an incident in which an unruly count asked this man “Who made you king?” Pope John XV rejected this king’s proposal to name Gerbert of Aurillac the Archbishop of Reims. This man was crowned in Noyon Cathedral after the death of (20 pts)",
        "Louis V in a hunting accident. This husband of Adelaide of Aquitaine pushed for the coronation of his son (10 pts)",
        "Robert the Pious early in his reign to secure succession in his newly founded dynasty. For 10 points, name this French king who founded a namesake royal house in 987."
      ],
      "answer": "Hugh Capet <CKM> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Giacomo Pilarino and Emanuel Timoni wrote letters describing this practice in the Ottoman Empire. Zabdiel Boylston observed empirical results of this practice in Massachusetts. Charles Maitland used this practice on the children of (20 pts)",
        "Lady Montagu, who spread it throughout Europe. A man who carried out this practice used lesions on the (10 pts)",
        "dairymaid Sarah Nelms and injected them into James Phipps. That form of this practice used cowpox. For 10 points, name this medical practice popularized by Edward Jenner, which conferred immunity against a viral disease."
      ],
      "answer": "inoculation against smallpox <JL> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The pseudonyms \"Cabu\" and \"Tignous\" were used by two members of this profession who had careers working for Stephane Charbonnier. A 2009 book by Brandeis professor Jytte Clausen had the work of a man in this profession excised due to a last-minute decision by (20 pts)",
        "Yale University Press. Kurt Westegaard was one of these people targeted after a 2005 controversy involving the (10 pts)",
        "Jyllands-Posten newspaper in Denmark. For 10 points, name these people who were targeted in early 2015 at the Charlie Hebdo newspaper for their offensive depictions of Muhammad."
      ],
      "answer": "political cartoonists <MJ> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A TV movie about this group resulted in Ruby Bates suing for being called a prostitute. While working for this group, Samuel Leibowitz proclaimed his trust in the \"God fearing people of Decatur.\" Victoria Price's accusations about this group used details from a (20 pts)",
        "Saturday Evening Post work of fiction. They were arrested in Paint Rock after being found \"hoboing\" on a freight train. This group's (10 pts)",
        "conviction was voided in the Supreme Court case Powell v. Alabama. For 10 points, name this group of nine black teenagers accused of raping two white women in 1931."
      ],
      "answer": "Scottsboro Boys <MC> {II}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Another member of this family defeated Richard Nixon in a 1962 election, but lost to (*) Ronald Reagan a few years later. That member of this family, Pat, was governor of his state during the Watts Riots. For 10 points, name this family of California Governor Jerry."
      ],
      "answer": "Brown <MC> {II} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 11"
    }
  ]
}